I'm a tourism entrepreneur and a peacebuilder,
أنا متعهد سياحة وباني للسلام،
but this is not how I started.
لكن لم تكن هذه بدايتي.
When I was seven years old, I remember watching television
عندما كنت في السابعة، أتذكر مشاهدتي للتلفاز
and seeing people throwing rocks,
ورؤيتي لأشخاص يرمون الحجارة،
and thinking, this must be a fun thing to do.
أعتقدت حينها أن ذلك شيئًا مسليًا.
So I got out to the street and threw rocks,
فخرجت إلى الشارع وبدأت أرمي الحجارة،
not realizing I was supposed to throw rocks at Israeli cars.
لم أدرك أنه كان يفترض بي رمي الحجارة على السيارات الإسرائيلية.
Instead, I ended up stoning my neighbors' cars. (Laughter)
حيث انتهى بي الأمر، أرمي سيارات جيراني. (ضحك)
They were not enthusiastic about my patriotism.
من المؤكد أنهم لم يتحمسوا لوطنيتي.
This is my picture with my brother.
هذه صورة لي مع أخي.
This is me, the little one, and I know what you're thinking:
ذلك أنا، الأصغر، اعلم بماذا تفكرون:
"You used to look cute, what the heck happened to you?"
"كنت تبدو لطيفًا، ماالذي حدث لك؟"
But my brother, who is older than me,
لكن أخي، والذي كان يكبرني سنًا،
was arrested when he was 18,
اعتقل عندما كان عمره ١٨ سنة،
taken to prison on charges of throwing stones.
وأُخذ إلى السجن بتهمة رمي الحجارة.
He was beaten up when he refused to confess that he threw stones,
تم ضربه حين رفض الاعتراف برميه للحجارة،
and as a result, had internal injuries
وبالنتيجة، تعرض لإصابات داخلية
that caused his death soon after he was released from prison.
أدت إلى وفاته مباشرة بعد أن أطلق سراحه.
I was angry, I was bitter,
كنت غاضبًا وحانقًا،
and all I wanted was revenge.
وكل ما أردته كان الإنتقام.
But that changed when I was 18.
لكن ذلك تغير حينما بلغت الـ ١٨ سنة.
I decided that I needed Hebrew to get a job,
قررت أني احتاج للغة العبرية للحصول على وظيفة
and going to study Hebrew in that classroom
عندما ذهبت لدراسة اللغة العبرية في ذلك الفصل
was the first time I ever met Jews who were not soldiers.
كانت تلك هي المرة الأولى التي أقابل فيها يهود ليسوا مجندين.
And we connected over really small things, like the fact that I love country music,
وتواصلنا عبر أشياء صغيرة جدًا، مثل حبي للموسيقى الريفية،
which is really strange for Palestinians.
والتي تعتبر غريبة جدًا على الفلسطينيين.
But it was then that I realized also that we have a wall of anger,
لكن حينها أدركت أيضاً أن هناك حائطًا من الغضب،
of hatred and of ignorance that separates us.
من الكره والجهل تفصلنا عن بعض.
I decided that it doesn't matter what happens to me.
قررت أنه لايهم ماحدث لي.
What really matters is how I deal with it.
بل مايهم هو كيف أتعامل معه.
And therefore, I decided to dedicate my life
وبالتالي، قررت أن أكرس حياتي
to bringing down the walls that separate people.
لهدم الجدران التي تفصل الناس.
I do so through many ways.
قمت بذلك بعدة طرق.
Tourism is one of them, but also media and education,
السياحة كانت واحدة منها، كما كان الإعلام والتعليم أيضًا،
and you might be wondering, really, can tourism change things?
قد تتساءلون، أحقًا ذلك، أيمكن للسياحة أن تحدث فرقًا؟
Can it bring down walls? Yes.
هل من الممكن أن تهدم الجدران؟ نعم.
Tourism is the best sustainable way to bring down those walls
السياحة هي أفضل طريقة مستدامة لهدم تلك الجدران
and to create a sustainable way of connecting with each other
وإنشاء طريق مستدام للتواصل مع بعضنا
and creating friendships.
وتكوين صداقات.
In 2009, I cofounded Mejdi Tours,
في عام ٢٠٠٩، شاركت في إنشاء مكتب مجدي للسياحة،
a social enterprise that aims to connect people,
مشروع اجتماعي يهدف لتواصل الناس،
with two Jewish friends, by the way,
مع صديقين يهوديين، بالمناسبة،
and what we'll do, the model we did,
وما سوف نفعله، هو النموذج الذي قدمناه،
for example, in Jerusalem, we would have two tour guides,
مثلًا، في القدس، كان لدينا دليلين سياحيين،
one Israeli and one Palestinian, guiding the trips together,
واحد إسرائيلي وواحد فلسطيني، يقودون الرحلات سويًا،
telling history and narrative and archaeology and conflict
يقصون التاريخ والحكاية وعلم الآثار والصراع
from totally different perspectives.
من وجهتي نظر مختلفة تمامًا.
I remember running a trip together with a friend named Kobi --
أتذكر قيادتي لرحلة سياحية سويًا مع صديق يدعى كوبي،
Jewish congregation from Chicago, the trip was in Jerusalem --
لطائفة يهودية من شيكاغو، كانت الرحلة في القدس،
and we took them to a refugee camp, a Palestinian refugee camp,
فأخذناهم إلى مخيم لاجئين، مخيم لاجئين فلسطينيين،
and there we had this amazing food.
وهناك تناولنا ألذ طعام.
By the way, this is my mother. She's cool.
بالمناسبة، تلك هي أمي. إنها رائعة.
And that's the Palestinian food called maqluba.
وتلك أكلة فلسطينية تسمى مقلوبة.
It means "upside-down."
وتعني "رأسًا على عقب."
You cook it with rice and chicken, and you flip it upside-down.
تطبخها مع الأرز والدجاج، ثم تقلبها رأسًا على عقب.
It's the best meal ever.
تعتبر ألذ وجبة على الإطلاق.
And we'll eat together.
أكلناها جميعًا.
Then we had a joint band, Israeli and Palestinian musicians,
توجهنا لفرقة موسيقية مشتركة، عازفين اسرائيلين وفلسطينيين
and we did some belly-dancing.
وقمنا ببعض الرقص الشرقي.
If you don't know any, I'll teach you later.
اذا لم تكونوا تعرفون الرقص، سأعلمكم لاحقًا.
But when we left, both sides,
عندما غادرنا، كل من الطرفين،
they were crying because they did not want to leave.
كانوا يبكون لأنهم لم يريدوا المغادرة.
Three years later, those relationships still exist.
بعدها بثلاث سنوات، لاتزال تلك العلاقات موجودة.
Imagine with me if the one billion people
تخيلوا معي لو أن المليار شخص
who travel internationally every year travel like this,
الذين يسافرون دوليًا كل عام، سافروا بهذه الطريقة،
not being taken in the bus from one side to another,
ولم ينتقلوا بالحافلة من جهة لآخرى،
from one hotel to another,
من فندق لآخر،
taking pictures from the windows of their buses of people and cultures,
والتقاط الصور من نوافذ الحافلات للناس والثقافات،
but actually connecting with people.
لكن تواصلوا مع الناس حقًا.
You know, I remember having a Muslim group from the U.K.
أتعلمون، كان لدي مجموعة من المسلمين من المملكة المتحدة.
going to the house of an Orthodox Jewish family,
ذهبوا لبيت عائلة يهودية أرثودوكسية،
and having their first Friday night dinners, that Sabbath dinner,
وتناولوا هناك أول عشاء ليالي الجمعة، عشاء السبت،
and eating together hamin, which is a Jewish food, a stew,
أكلوا الخامن سويًا، وهي أكلة يهودية، من الخنة،
just having the connection of realizing, after a while,
وبعد التواصل أدركوا، وبعد فترة،
that a hundred years ago, their families came out
أن عوائلهم قدموا قبل مئة سنة ماضية
of the same place in Northern Africa.
من نفس المكان في شمال أفريقيا.
This is not a photo profile for your Facebook.
هذه ليست صورة عرض لحسابك في فيسبوك.
This is not disaster tourism.
هذه ليست سياحة كارثية.
This is the future of travel,
هذا هو مستقبل السياحة،
and I invite you to join me to do that, to change your travel.
وأنا ادعوكم للإنضمام إلي في فعل ذلك، لتغيير سفركم.
We're doing it all over the world now,
نحن نقوم بذلك في كل أنحاء العالم الآن،
from Ireland to Iran to Turkey,
من إيرلندا إلى إيران وتركيا،
and we see ourselves going everywhere to change the world.
نحن نرى أنفسنا نذهب إلى كل مكان لتغيير العالم.
Thank you.
شكرًا لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)